Name: Sharif Jbour Contact email: sharif.jbour@gmail.com

Nationality: Jordanian Date of Birth: 14 Dec 1975

Senior expert on biodiversity conservation with more than 20 years of experience in the Middle East region, work mainly included designation and conservation of Important Bird and Biodiversity Areas – IBAs, Key Biodiversity Areas – KBAs, research and monitoring & conservation of Globally Threatened Species. Evaluation of IBAs against global and regional criteria (including sites' delineation and digitization), assisting in fund raising and training (Bird Identification, IBA criteria and managing Databases).

Other main engagement include implementation of the Critically Endangered AEWA (African Eurasian Migratory Water bird Agreement) Single Species Action Plan - **SSAP** in the Middle East (Northern Bald Ibis and Sociable Lapwing) across their ranges in Syria, Iraq, Saudi Arabia and Yemen, and coordination of the Redlisting process and evaluation.

Key regional initiatives coordination including water bird conservation in the Middle East in addition to update and conservation planning of the critical sites network - **CSN** for water birds, and coordination of the implementation of conservation projects for globally threatened birds. Recently was engaged in identification of follow up on conservation management of Key Biodiversity Areas-**KBAs** in the East Mediterranean.

Education

The University of Jordan, BSc. in Biological Science, Amman/Jordan, January 1999.

Employment

| 2012 - present | Program Officer - Middle East, Critical Ecosystem Partnership Fund (CEPF) |
|----------------|---|
| | Regional Implementation Team (RIT), BirdLife International – Middle East |
| | Secretariat |

The **Critical Ecosystem Partnership Fund - CEPF** is a joint initiative of l'Agence Française de Développement, Conservation International, the European Union, the Global Environment Facility, the Government of Japan and the World Bank.

Responsible for the effective implementation of the CEPF Mediterranean Basin investment in the Middle East. Main duties include stakeholder engagement, reviewing grant applications, capacity building, technical advice to funded projects, project planning, monitoring and evaluating projects, network building and knowledge sharing. Countries covered under this scope: Lebanon, Jordan, Palestine and Egypt.

2006 - 2012 Regional Conservation Manager, BirdLife International – Middle East Secretariat

- Implementation of the CR Critically Endangered AEWA (African Eurasian Migratory Water bird Agreement) Single Species Action Plan SSAP in the Middle East (Northern Bald Ibis and Sociable Lapwing)
- Coordinator of the regional red listing update

Country Program Coordinator (Syria and Iraq) Syria:

- Coordinator of the Northern Bald Ibis **NBI** Conservation Program, and Sociable Lapwing **SL (both are Critically Endangered Species)** and developing National Species Action Plan
- Monitoring of Species population trend and identification of urgent conservation actions

- Developing Local Conservation Group initiative linked to conservation (including revival of Hima approach) 2005 2010.
- Coordinator of National Wetland Surveys (IWC International Waterbird Census) at wetland IBAs Iraq: coordinator of BirdLife Iraq conservation program
- Coordinator of the CIMI Canada Iraq Marshland Initiative 2005 2008
- Coordinator of Iraq Mesopotomia surveys (IWC and summer breeding surveys)

Regional Coordinator Critical Site Network - Middle East

- Regional Water Bird Officer
- Coordinator of the Regional component of **CSN** Critical Site Network Tool
- Developing Standard Survey Methodologies and Monitoring Schemes
- Technical Advisor for the WOW Demonstration Project for Middle East Aden/Yemen

Hima Fund Coordinator - Qatar 2005 - 2010

Helping with issuing calls for proposals, review proposals and support grantees in the region.

Ornithological Society of the Middle East (OSME) Conservation Research Fund (technical committee member)

Review and evaluate received applications for granting.

2000 – 2006 Regional IBAs Coordinator, BirdLife International – Middle East Secretariat

Evaluation of IBAs against global and regional criteria (including sites' delineation and digitization), Assist in fund raising and training (Bird Identification, IBA criteria and managing DataBases), Update the regional website of BirdLife Middle East, and regional coordination of World Bird Festival **WBF.**

Implementation and updating the Global IBA Monitoring Framework through the BirdLife's web enabled **WBDB** - World Bird Database for the Middle East, and Manager of BirdLife's World Bird DataBase for the Middle East

1999 – 2000 Researcher, Important Bird Areas (IBAs) of Jordan, BirdLife International – Middle East Secretariat and the Royal Society for the Conservation of Nature(Jordan)

Field research to identify IBAs of Jordan

Qualifications and Skills

- Good computer literate, including computer graphic design programs
- Good knowledge of managing and updating Databases
- Good knowledge in technical report writing and monitoring indicators
- Good photographic skills
- PADI licensed Diver (Open Water Diver)

Language skills

Arabic (Mother tongue)

English (fluent both reading and writing)

Project Examples

- Prepared rapid assessment for birds and the fauna in an initial site assessment and concept plan for the formal management of the newly established King Salman Royal Natural Reserve, Saudi Arabia. Spring 2019.
- A preliminary assessment of the scope and scale of illegal killing and taking of wild birds in the Arabian peninsula, Iran and Iraq, 2019.

- Important Bird and Biodiversity Areas in the UAE, 2018.
- Main researcher for Important Bird Areas of Jordan.
- Coordinator of the Northern Bald Ibis NBI Conservation Program, and Sociable Lapwing (both are Critically Endangered Species) and developing National Species Action Plan.
- Participated in Environmental Assessment and Monitoring Study /Jordan Compensation Claim for the Gulf Crisis submitted to the UNCC.
- Led work for the Environmental Assessment Disi –Mudawarra to Amman Water Conveyance System.
- Ecological researcher at Jordan Valley Preliminary Land Use Master Plan Project Environment, Socio-economic and Socio-cultural Dimensions.
- Participated in development of national guidelines for wind energy development in Jordan.
- Aqaba South Port and Industrial Zone Master Planning Project Environmental Planning.
- Research on migratory birds in Northern Saudi Arabia, 2015, Preliminary Survey of the Critically Endangered Sociable Lapwing (*Vanellus gregarious*) in Northern Saudi Arabia.
- Researcher conservation, Aden wetlands Yemen
- Conducted several ecological studies in the field of Protected Areas and development projects in Iraq, Kuwait, Syria, Saudi Arabia and Jordan